right welcome to this week's solution
raising today we are talking about a
topic suicide which can be hard for a
lot of people and would anybody like to
start and share what this means to them
currently how it's impacted their life
or what they see happening in the world
you can just pause and unpause roots
sorry muting on you I mean there's two
parts to this isn't there really there's
there's suicide people who you know
can't handle the circumstances of their
lives and you know ending it is better
than plowing on and then there's people
who are you know suffering from whatever
it might be some sort of degenerative
illness you know what I mean and and
sort of wish to end the bombing I guess
they're similar I guess they're similar
in a way though I don't think of them as
the same but actually now that I'm
talking it's now I'm saying out loud I
guess they are pretty similar so yeah I
mean until recently it's been a criminal
offence to commit suicide which is
ridiculous because if you're successful
then obviously you can't be prosecuted
for it but anyone who helps you is a
criminal and so it seems to be in the
wrong domain somehow in our current
world you know the whole conversation
about suicide seems to be in in the
wrong domain it's a health issue or it's
a criminal issue criminal justice issue
and that just seems to be I mean you
know if your health is there's no
recuperating you're in pain all the time
why should you not have the right to end
your life in in a in a suffering free
way so yeah i it feels like it's it
feels like it's in the wrong place in
our culture at the moment but then death
in general is weirdly peculiarly treated
in our culture and so I guess this is
maybe just a minute another
manifestation of that so yeah I'm
drifting now so I'll shut up thank you
Eric Kerri did you want to go oh you
were started yeah well basically hurt
right I call I come from being in care
and being homeless for quite some time
and because if it wasn't for one guy
doggie and
and the council for a single homeless I
wouldn't be here and cuz I went to his
organization for now but because of
didn't tick all the boxes mm there's
nothing they could do for me like us
because I was single on my own it didn't
have kids it didn't have mental health
problems and wasn't a drug addict so
basically I'll fuck off till you find
something else right so if it wasn't for
him and he had a bit of faith in me when
I was none in myself so I think just um
just having that and years ago I tried
because I got on my feet after a while
and went back to try it up and that was
that was triggered by my friend killing
himself
Christmas Eve he threw himself out of
his window and died and because of that
I'd seen a lot of people who were going
downhill and the current state of things
is you basically have to wait to get in
the gutter and you're beyond out before
all the organizations or kick in and you
know you don't have to be mentally ill
to be wasn't I sort of like don't want
to be living the life you live in
anymore and a lot of it is say some
stances dictate who you meet and him so
that that's why I'm kind of like as I
said I tried setting something up nobody
got what I was on about nobody could see
the benefit of having connections and
having somebody there just to maybe hold
your hand a bit till you've got enough
faith in yourself to keep on going and
as I said if it wasn't for him I
probably wouldn't be near as I said I
did try and go back and failed which I
was obviously going in a wrong way and
probably because I was a copy cow and I
seen what was wrong but nobody would
want to take any notice anyway so so
yeah so that's basically and as I said
you have to wait till even the gutter
oh you're beyond doubt people you can
actually get any help and then the girly
help that I see out there is like the
article to us bill you have to be
defaced by a doctor and you know if
you're not in those situations or if
you're not you know you don't feel like
you're mental you've got mental health
issues you're not going to go to the
hospital and get up and if you don't
have any family you don't have any kids
and you know a lot of people who are now
they are kids so that stops them doing
it and we ex-partner of 18 years he's so
like bipolar major depressive disorder
it took me seven years
trying to get him out and he said he
still wants to sort like wake up dead
everyday you know I mean but it's a
level of self self-hatred that today
that I haven't been able to sorta like
help with but he started to get a wee
bit better now cause that does took me
about 18 years I've kind of been around
for them and now you know so that that's
where I'm coming from with this I've
seen different ways from where I'm
working just about talking with them
when you come to the solutions and hey
if you carry Josh what do you wanna sure
if we're talking about suicide and what
that looks like right now in society and
anything you Padma sure enough my last
year of high school a friend kills
herself and he just there were no
warning signs nothing like he was I
talked to her that same day and he is
happy and laughing and then he um he got
like a he got accused of cheating dirty
German class and I don't know whether
she was actually eating or not but
anyway he got accused of cheating and he
left the school and and walked for a
while and walked into the river and
after that like people were looking for
her and stuff and I feel like I I was
really upset at the time not just
because of that but also because the
school handled it very badly
they didn't um they I didn't feel like
they did all they could have done to
prevent it they he wrote a suicide note
but see if the teachers had gone out
right then and tried to find her they
might have been able to but instead they
they just asked the cops to find her and
the cops were during we're having a
shift change and they like took a while
to get around to it and then afterwards
they tried to cover it up so this was
the start of me distrusting Authority
now I'm starting to come
not this chance 232 much as if has it
last year but this was a big event in my
life type for me I've been depressed the
pen anxiety I but I've never I've never
been suicidal but when I was postpartum
I was just so lonely and overwhelmed as
a single mom and I just was in crisis
and I didn't know where to turn so I
phoned the suicide hotline cuz all I
could think of there'd be someone on the
other line and it was like nobody
answered it was like voicemail will call
you back it's like if I was in crisis
and a lot of what carrie said that um
like it's like they need you to say yes
i want to kill myself if they offer you
any help and I was like I'm desperate
but no that's not I'm here because I
want to be here and if there's nothing
offered and then one of my best friends
right before my daughter was born he
killed himself and it was in crisis I
know people who've been in long-term
mental pain and eventually they choose
like assisted suicide whether it's
physical or mental or pain and that
feels different than being in crisis and
you only have to make it through a week
or two before you then aren't suicidal
then you don't I mean you it and there's
something about it happening when it's
in crisis that makes me even more guilty
like one of my last year I was
house-sitting for someone who was going
to a funeral and the funeral they went
to is for his cousin who had who had
killed himself and I had a conversation
with him beforehand he was like yeah he
was in pain and he'd been talking about
it for a decade and now he's in peace
and he's at peace and so it was a
different feeling for that family then
then my friend who happens to also be
named Erik and I'm holding his necklace
because it's a significant part of game
be and my journey and it's just you know
to be here but I also in society in
general when someone's suicidal the
option is to go to the psychiatric ward
to be admitted and that's like hospital
meets prison
two of the worst things I can imagine
I've ever been in like I've never been
in one myself as a patient but I've
visited other people and it's just I
know that after they've been there
they're so less likely to ask for help
because they know that's where they're
gonna end up so if they tell their
friends or family that they're suicidal
then that's where they end up and it
just seems like there could be a much
more compassionate option and then also
this fact that like anything medical we
have to leave it up to the medical
community so if you're suicidal you
should be talking to a psychiatrist but
do you have access to a psychiatrist
what if we were peer to peer isn't it
better than nothing what if you could
just say hey I need someone to be with
me right now because I'm gonna I'm going
through a 36-hour crisis and have
somebody there physically present with
you or answer I'm getting on too many
more many more are the topics but even
just like I try hard to lose it for my
vocabulary but we talk about people
committing suicide and it's because of
the crying part of it right they
committed a crime and that's no longer
you know the PC term for it but it's
still part of the vocabulary and it's
you know as you the shameful thing you
weren't strong enough instead of how we
like think about people who are battling
cancer for a long period of time and
then are no longer here you know they're
still they're still brave and have
thought and if you fought depression for
ten years twenty years thirty years I
just don't I we can do better for each
other so now we can have a little more
of an open discussion for what's going
on in this space of suicide in society
and then we feel we can move on to the
next or in a few minutes we'll move on
to what this could look like in a
society that maybe didn't fear death and
had mental health and peer support and
connection community well I've been up a
look at some of the research and from
the UK and from the Samaritans mostly
the people who were committing suicide
thought you know decided to end their
emotion just mostly men young men and an
older man who seemed to be more likely
to do so so
is it IIIi think the majority of that is
mostly circumstances and under the
feeling of lonely less mystified as you
mentioned and answer said they may not
want a bit and the relatives and not so
they've bought this kindness of
strangers and now it's easier to talk to
a stranger about how you feeling but you
don't know whether that strangers gonna
take what you told them and you know
turns out to be one of the biggest
concert the world you know I mean you
don't know so it'd be nice you know like
to have someone there who's if you tell
someone that you're going to go through
stuff tell someone they're just to
listen listen first and I know a lot of
the Samaritan stuff I know they offer
they don't open any advice they're there
to listen they can't offer you any
advice at all so that's all very well
and good
Boyan and ships it circumstances that
it's not really gonna change the
circumstances just having somebody to
listen to so I think it you need to meet
people where that look a look at way so
like what's going on in the life what's
going on around them and and take that
from there and then maybe find people
who'd be willing 12 or maybe come up
with solutions for them to maybe get out
of them shitty situations you know
because I know through being homeless
and jobless and trying the China try it
yeah it just sucks the life out yeah and
people and you know you meet these
people who sorta like happy clappy i hey
let's be joyous
you know think yourself think yourself
happy you again and you just want to
punch him in the face because you're
just taking you've got no clue mate you
know i mean them so if someone's there
to listen ball so to offer practical
solutions as well um in terms of right
and just Pat being there and just maybe
alternate and till he feels so like
strong enough and just making sure that
you stay with them till till it's you
know the ready to stand on their own
feet because what you don't find see if
you go and help someone like that
without well so like saying you you know
I'm helping you because you have to go
and help loads of people you'd often
find the most people who go back and
help others by the ones
we've had help but they've out there
help with no conditions
there's no no conditions attached no
strings and they've gone and done that
without you know because you know how
the value of what happens you know
what's been given to them freely and
without and this I love it you know
there's a lot of religious organizations
that allow people out but you know
you'll make them you know let's go be
religious and that like for instance our
way for the Christian Science place I'm
not a Christian Science but the you have
this kind of retreat place they were
people calm and that and the people are
really nice and I've been chatting to
loads of them about that without scaring
them for the most people are scared to
me anyway and but they're they they have
an empty house which could be with empty
beds but they they call because of the
way they're set up as a charity they you
know we can't you know be Leland put
other people as well which i think is it
just a bit of a waste fairly you know
but that's that's going into the
solution idea you know I mean I wanted
to touch on sorry what you said about
talk of what I call toxic positivity the
like you know when you look at who kills
themselves in celebrities a lot of it as
comedians right so it's like you look
happy on the outside and how much of
that pervades society that if you have
to pretend to happy the underlying
you're probably a bit more miserable and
the phenomenon that when somebody in the
media kills themselves and there's a
news story that there's more people who
end up killing themselves yeah and so
like talking about it seems to make it
worse and not talking about it makes it
worse and we're not solving it and we're
not meeting people where they are and so
no about friends right on the you know
the McDonough said well you know just
let's revel in them Italy together and
that seems to source like you know shift
it a bit you know I mean so if you
feeling down and then oh come on let's
let's do together you know and then cuz
I have a darker a bit of a dark and
twisted sense of humor which probably
doesn't go down down well in some
quarters for them yeah as I said you've
gotta meet people where that are and not
tie in force you know what may be a way
to me might not work for other people
but if you meet the way
find out what's going on in their lives
what what's causing them to think like
that or drag them to that point then you
can start seeing okay then well let's
try this you know I mean you know I'm
sorry carry this move next part by just
wanted Josh where do you have your hand
up are you wanting to say something it
was a fairly good transition Carrie
you're welcome to start the next section
if you want to share a beautiful version
of the future that you would like to
live in in this space it can be 5 10 100
years in the future however long you
need it to be in the future for it to be
potentially possible in your minds and
they don't need to match so we have to
the beautiful feature right well you
know like you get loads of the places
I'd like to have phoenix lighthouses all
over the world and then be like these
little kinds of places where you go
there you just say like I'm feeling
really sure right come and stay for two
weeks and they were you know see how
that is but yeah that lights out them in
various light out so like you're nine
great people but the face to face is
really important
they're in each city in town there's you
know you can feel if you you're
struggling you could just go along even
if you just want to turn off for the day
for the cup of tea um or just want to
maybe stay over so if you know kind of
like run like a bed-and-breakfast kind
of idea but the idea we're over it would
be a sort of like a retreat place
because you know as I said you go to
hospital there's no way to go or just
easily treat places the cost should
afford you but as I said there'll be a
lot of it so they activities arts and
crafts and things related and stuff as
well you know it mean so all these
little houses all over the place so that
would tie into the 10,000 people that
that's what I would look so like all
faiths unknown didn't matter anyway
where you come from being able to have a
space where he'd actually come and stay
and if you just wanted a bear peace and
quiet and have people there who was
actually know half the year and actually
cared about yeah and then that care
could you've been there you wouldn't be
like well we're just here taking your
money
bye-bye no don't that relationship would
be built from time today
you die you know I mean not that that's
what I'd love you know I mean thank you
anyone else like to share their really
like that idea of a place where people
can go where it's not gonna cost them
any money right the third place where
people can go where whatever people have
got similar experiences just they're you
know the refuge oh I really like that
idea and I was when I'm coming back to
my original thing I am separating again
in my head now that the suicide brought
about by the pressures of life and the
inability to face those pressures for
whatever reason and whatever those
freshness might be versus the chronic
illness type euthanasia right we if we
call it two different things right you
can idea being that and suicide being
the response the circumstances of life
rather than illness
I would actually watch the euthanasia
made a lot easier and and and the stigma
around it go away you know that this
this whole hanging on to life at all
costs kind of thing it seems we don't do
it to our pets you know what I mean we
don't do it to anything else why do we
insist on it for our parents our
children whatever just you know this
sanctity of life bullshit
so yeah that that needs needs
reevaluation would be it's not really an
issue in and of itself is it it's it's a
symptom of a whole load of other things
that are going wrong in the world
so yeah it's tricky to talk about in and
of itself without because and unless the
world itself is a much more hospitable
place in relationships healthier and
there's less you know lying and
disinformation and and and rival risk
competition kind of thing I mean this is
what creates the soil for the
circumstances after which people wish to
commit suicide right here they inability
to pay their debts that they've been you
know a group that was everything to them
whatever it might be you know what I
mean though so yeah it's a symptom so
it's hard to talk about what I would
like to see
because what I want to see is the world
things were into a place where not so
many people feel the need to commit
suicide you know I mean yeah it has a
definitely an intertwined problem my
beautiful world is that where we've
taken care of each other's needs we know
I love carry suggestion of having a
retreat you can go to where you know
somewhere you know you're looked after
and I think that is is you feel like
you're not important or even if you're
you're a burden on your family and
you're not contributing you're not to be
able to be able to go somewhere you like
we even if we don't know you because
they're not your friends and family we
love you just you're human we love you
enough to take care of you and then I
think there's a natural reciprocity that
comes out of that but it's large
percentage of those people are gonna
come back and serve the next generation
right the next group of people who's
who's in crisis right then and to be
able to just know that there's somewhere
you can go and there's a crisis and to
have connected communities that you feel
part of and you feel like you have a
purpose and to be able to I think what
Eric suggested having euthanasia
euthanasia actually be easier is a
ironic solution because if you know that
that's an option one of the people I
like to listen to on YouTube and stuff
is called teal Swan and she's
controversial because she actually had a
video about suicide talking about how
people who are suicidal like the fact we
sent him to psychiatry like to the psych
ward is about the worst thing we could
do and one of the things that she did
when she was suicidal and that she
suggests is that they actually do have a
plan because when you have a plan and
you have like there's that option and
you can live this day because that's
always I could always do that tomorrow
and if you're getting help but there's
something about that if we had it as a
possibility an actual humane you could
tell your family and you know this is
happening on this day that you're less
likely to actually do it because it's a
possibility that's not doesn't contain
shame and doesn't contain like it's your
life and you get to choose and there's
all of these options available to you
and that is an option you get to pick
because it's your life yeah I was a
creamy top because I guess that the
Santa Clara so like a dignity and
assistant
because you know you need a roll doc
Dignitas where you so they coiled into
the back of a camper van in Switzerland
you know I mean well yeah because I
think you know a key if you do that was
paid and like you know the people who
thought and campaigned to having the
right to die and then feed so they you
know no sorry you can't you can't you
know we're the focus anybody else to
tell you I would win that you want to go
you know I mean and I said she said if
you know you family know that you go in
and then at least you can sort of like
up them around you saying goodbye rather
than being sat on you know and it's some
sort of like up you know army this it's
just it's just sad you know I mean what
do you have a future you would like to
share feel free to chime in if you think
of anything and we can just have a
conversation I just like to give you the
option well there's so much potential in
this space and that's also like talking
about something that is somewhat
negative connotation which is part of
the problem of suicide is thinking about
beautiful future not where it doesn't
exist but where it's greatly reduced
because it's naturally produced it's not
shaming people out of it it's not toxic
positivity and people out of which we
know doesn't work and so the idea of
having people who've been there done
that helping people who are currently
going through it without the shame truly
meeting them where they're at is I think
a beautiful option that would benefit
both parties the people who've been
there and the people who are currently
there and yet our societies and set up
for that because you're not a
psychiatrist
so the legalities of all of that is is a
problem
so my guess my beautiful future says
fuck the laws fuck legality yeah let's
actually care about saving people and if
it's better to have peer-to-peer and I'm
more likely to call a friend or stranger
friends than I am to call 9-1-1 then I
should have that option yeah
and that was the irony of the two
ominous earlier on and I mean Samaritans
are great which is right they can't
actually do anything right all they can
do is talk to you and so if that kind of
thing could be expanded I mean I really
coming that's what Kerry said before the
it's great idea doing that an
organization like the Samaritans but
expand it to include refuges and actual
help to do actual things to put your
life right you know what I mean that
would be that would be that would be
great something like that yeah and I
mean I know we're we're a little bit
before time but you know the possible
proximate or whatever it's called any
scale right I mean you could bring up a
few friends and say listen should we
should we offer to the rest of the
community a little bit of counseling for
people that want to you know I mean and
then who's got a spare room that they
could put someone up in for a week or
two while they get back on their feet
there's no reason this couldn't be
organized at a very very small scale
with a few people at the community level
right no reason in the world there's one
of the guys I'm telling you I'm just
about to do a podcast series because
then there was this place but if you do
add asked could I do a podcast but I got
told because I wasn't mentally ill that
I couldn't play it play out with them
but there's a guy John who is part of
that and have been speaking to part of
this group to do a podcast because I
know he's done one on on so like anxiety
he's on Comcast so I was thinking about
maybe so like working with him to
develop what he's done and help him
because he's on his own I think doing it
so him I'm so yeah I definitely think
that that would be a good idea you know
but I'm hopefully hopefully a my can get
more people to come and chat about I'll
be feel you know I mean
on a podcast level maybe and share the
feelings and that and because I know
this the stuff it sent out which is just
a photo for me open envelopes and they
are for a place that people can go in a
softener for mental health issues well I
think it's just mental people with
mental health issues where as you know
people who is not just mental health
issues that cause people to you know
take their own lives not well I know
they probably get funded so they
probably have to tick all those boxes so
be nice to Salt Lake up an organization
think you did enough to tick boxes you
didn't have to fit a criteria you could
just go so well yeah yeah I've gotta
start in our and I'd like to want to
give me a house if someone wants to give
me a house because like well when I was
sick because the place was way again
they dinner like they've closed down so
put in a proposal and all the proposals
were you know for because I'm not a
Christian Scientist they kind of keep me
at arm's length will be taken what the
proposal looked on I'm trying to duck
that but the kind of missing the point
and but that's okay well it's the as I
said give me an idea so they yeah if we
could find somebody to give me a house
breath free to say like five years then
because because then you're not worried
about having to pay the mortgage to pay
the rent and then you're havin to
develop services that may be no good to
anybody just to get the money in you
know I mean so that's why I think
something like 10,000 people and under
grant that would kick it off quite
nicely thank you very much check but
you'd have to find 10,000 people to
actually give a shit I think this is a
beautiful transition into unless
everyone's any one thing else they want
to share about their beautiful future of
the adjacent possible which is what
could we do with 10,000 people and
$100,000 because Carrie was sparking
things in need so probably just shut up
please cuz I have a tendency to so they
probably thought about this because
there is something I've been thinking
about for a long time you know so yeah
so got these little ideas in my head but
just you pop it out and scaring people
away mostly you know yeah
that's what I was thinking because
because there's part of me that's like
right someone's gonna give you a house
right like I'm so like if that's money
that's and I was like no no actually
people care enough about this there's
empty hoses all over the place they
don't have to do the work and they only
have to donate their house for five for
Friday nights I need to get a tax
deductible credit you know what we could
Vantage oh you know like the air dove
air be it is tanked because all the
Quebec can own it tell mid-nineteen and
all of that all yet people who bought
houses to rent out to their B&Bs right
they'll have empty properties you know I
mean so if we've got someone thought I
was an empty air B&B property that the
be Carmine's house anymore for whatever
reason they give it to me well give it
to me we could find them in all
different areas and if they just give us
look like alleyway of five years just
all right let's start this let's let's
see what we can do and then that five
years because said because if we ran
three and that we could actually you
know take care of the empty building for
them and I've it running in such a way
and then develop projects and and things
that come out of that there was help
sorta like be self-sufficient because
the last thing I want to be doing is
certain things off and then average to
go to people for money and going oh you
don't take all our boxes you know I mean
because that would just be that would
just devastate me that would you know I
mean so but yeah if you have ten
thousand people like so when I'm I've
been out of empty properties around the
world you know so I'm yeah there are
someone with farmland where they're
living on their property but they're
willing to you know you can come and
build a small house I don't know if that
would work for what you're doing but
like having people in their own little
spot and that might not work for this
particular thing because they're gonna
be isolated in their own will host but
that Mike I would want that if I was a
nun to prices to be able to get away and
be part of connection yeah but I mean
alternative solutions to be everywhere
I'm being able to find I think this is
the one space a lot of times it's like
ten thousand people needs to solve it
for them or they're not gonna be willing
to give money to it I will go ahead
you know 10,000 people I think that
we've lost people the suicide so we do
deeply care about it and so even if it's
not gonna be me there I would have 10
colors I'm up to this well I see sighs
apparently there's one in five people or
an endangered of Scilly killer
themselves that's what in size so if
you've got 10,000 people i doesn't said
you could on this as kind of like a bed
and breakfast or after them 10,000
people they know if they wanted to come
and stay you know I mean those surveys
they would so they come and stay and say
and you know and even if they didn't
want he could just come and stay and if
you wanted to help out and and that as
well you know I mean and and I was
thinking about people who have them do
it so like I've disabilities right but
the function and disabilities but we
can't get jobs and then the ends up
losing homes especially in the states
you get so much but the the what you get
doesn't even cover in rent so they're at
the mercy of living at you know maybe in
people's basements and stuff like that
so you could get them to be so like
caretakers of the building and therefore
they're you know obviously the built you
know if the operators are B&B and you'd
of staff or not and then they would be
the caretakers they'd have a home these
up and that we're for people you know I
mean so that they're for you looking
after them as well you know I mean so it
kind of so they you know it can fix it a
lot of things you know it means so yeah
so we add love 10,000 people where do we
get them from the future conversation
but it also is like having one house
right they can cater to six people at a
time or four people in time and over
that number is is it powerful adjacent
possible right that is like six people
who are gonna live a little bit longer
and whatever they're going to reach the
world but there's also the possibility
of what you're trying to do in the world
right Carrie is you're like there's a
puzzle to put together which is okay we
need a property we need people who are
gonna be on that property and gonna be
the stewards we need people who are
gonna look after the property we need
food we need to be able to so it'll put
those things together maybe I never want
to have a conversation someone cuz I
can't handle that for mental health but
I can x2 right
so I come and cook and be able to put
out that map and that network so that
you know whatever country you're in you
can find the Airbnb of people and and
with the legality of right we're not
psychiatrists right where the Samaritans
where the equivalent we're like we're
doing what we can and we're hoping you
come back to do and we'll see how
successful we are and how many people
come back and how many people here I
don't like coming to the UK and that you
can cope right if my my little plan was
having these houses all over the place
right so each one would have their own
separate wing but if you say if you
wanted to go within another house you
could actually go you'd be paid for
where you're at
or you could come on over as a tourist
so you'd be like a tourist but you'd
also be like helping to find out about
the local community build up networks
within that community tap into what
services are on offer so you'd have six
months of fines and out I'm just getting
to know a different place getting to
know different people and then taking
that and then using that as the kind of
like little notice all right
relationship marketing would be like I
don't know I listened to your marketing
one thing you did and I was like yeah
totally agree I ate marketing it's all
shade you know I really don't own your
treatment often so yeah so relationship
marketing is all about getting to know
the actual people you come and and as I
said give them a people who work in the
different places a chance to come and
just live for six months say like come
to the UK for six months live in the
house find out a lot of stuff because
sometimes it takes an outsider to find
out more about the local area so and
then you wouldn't because there's way
ahead because you'd be like fact-finding
but you'd be paid from over there so and
then you could you could ask them people
go into different countries all over the
world you know I mean so you wouldn't be
sort of a shock in the one place but
ever you know I mean so I'm saying I've
thought about this a lot to me like all
right is there any other potential
possibilities that aren't necessarily a
physical location for me want to go to
that are open for me what this sparks is
my other project that's not actually a
project in any way but that I'd use
which is the five question
like something the way it's structured I
don't know what that would help people
in crisis because even though what is
because the questions are Who am I who
are my people what is my purpose what do
I need and what am i ready to let go of
and with a slight tweak I think like
what is my purpose like what is my next
step forward right who am i what am i
I'd like to be able to to be able to
have a peer group to look at that with
maybe it's not tackling people who are
in suicidal crisis but it's helping
people not get to suicidal crisis right
now looking out what is that it's having
a purpose it's having connections it's
having and even then you can go into
crisis right but if you're way more
resilience and not able to because you
don't know you can fall down you know
you can fall apart and you have but you
have a system that helps you yeah and a
system that connects you with any number
of those things right like maybe five
questions is one option and there's you
can find a peer group and I would love
to get 10,000 people together who used
to be suicidal who had a suicidal crisis
at one point in time and what got you
through it right what actually why were
you in it and then what got you through
it maybe you run into more so then
you're like oh we need a divorce
category right like and when people go
through divorce they can be connected to
this so they're less likely oh you got
an F in school and like teenagers have a
different level of crisis that is like
they don't have the capacity to see the
big picture and they feel the shame and
like someone posted and make a photo of
them online right and like how
catastrophic that is but having people
be able to share yes I've been there now
it's better and yes the internet might
be freaking out on you like here's a
safe space of peers that I've been there
done that
right like yours here's another 12
teenagers that is hopping bullying the
kids to take their own lives now as I
said I wasn't a kid so now you don't get
cheers over me as getting kicked it you
know being under those people there's
one guy in there who actually his mother
used to send him to school in those
shoes on schuster separates the house
no he got moved to a boys hostel and he
ended up in a mental hospital after that
and he was just such a lovely guy and he
just got destroyed you know you know
that I will just say and there's a lot
of kids who are coming out okay
you've got no families
you know I mean but there's nobody's I
did got maybe foster care to maybe 18
maybe 21 after lucky like there's
there's nothing not enough there and
they've today coming out with no
families no family structure you know I
mean and the people I was in care with
it you know people have said three well
you're one of the lucky ones you've
actually survived there but you know
what with me as if one was in bed lost
bill and there's all sort of shit that's
gone on you know I mean so in yeah said
I just it'd be nice to have a place
online where you could actually have a
safe space well Joe just stopped out
from sort of like you know predatory
people invade in that space you know and
and you know that's you know but that
would be a warrior mine you know so they
you know because I know a lot of people
kinda like to harvest some people who
are already vulnerable a so how would
you out of 10,000 people how would you
get it's a stage where those 10,000
people wouldn't be doing you know the
you know wouldn't be telling what
answers are they do it for their own
honorable purposes you know I mean I
would you don't you I would you how
would you bet that you know well that's
perfect part of the process is is more
what can 10,000 people create it's not
necessarily I didn't quite sorry I was
talking to my kid yeah send it to the
printer son but that like was it
something about like confidentiality of
ten thousand people are hearing there
because I've seen people you can to
others and users to think or to you know
they haven't received them with so they
you know with any kind of care or you
know I mean and they just basically
gonna destroy them you know I mean and
it's just it's just sad watch enough
because they've just gone and don't know
for their own pace or a bouquet of hazel
paper since you know me just because I
can you know I mean so out as I said you
know not everybody in the Wales call
good soul and he wants to help people or
not you know so we gotta watch out for
that as well like so I don't know how he
is actually create something that was
you'd be able to spot the signs of
somebody actually doing that you know
way as
though everything told me I'd be to be
had quite some time so sorry my my kids
really excited about her video game
she's currently playing just got
something new but um that there's the
possibility like there are all these
places out there
right there's rehab places there's
psychiatric units to be able to have the
option of the people who've been there
and been customers of there to give
their opinion of it right like oh my
parents put me in gay conversion therapy
I give it negative a million stars like
to be able to see and then then it's
gonna weed out like just to just shine a
spotlight on the people out there that
have nefarious and it might be that's
for some people it works and for some
people it doesn't right boy be for some
people a tough love approach in their
teen years was exactly what they needed
and with other people they needed
something different right so you then we
can figure out what matches people more
um but there are ways to work on that
like maybe it's not us tackling the
actual it's like what is currently
happening in this space and then how do
people get help and how helpful is that
and that is like with the teal Swan
thing she was controversial because one
of her people one of the people who
follow her committed suicide why help
themselves and then their parent was
like oh it's all teal Swan and no
because would she have still done it if
she'd been in the other one and that's
kind of like no one looks at the doctor
the psychiatrist and says okay well ten
of your your patients did but literally
anyone outside of the profession if
anyone kills themselves you're legally
liable if you like took that on in any
way from the outside and it's like well
no because there's the option was
nothing or her and she might have helped
her live longer you don't know and so
like what what are the statistics that
actually are people living longer under
this or not are people choosing today
and if they are not is it a beautiful
kasi right like I don't know what the
metrics are and I think people who've
been in that crisis would be a better
people to say what those metrics are
than someone who hasn't mm-hmm why do we
do this haha in a plumby way well this
is to generate the idea that there are
possibilities that you could do a 10,000
$100,000 and what I would love is for
other people to do solution raisins to
have not just one conversation about
what we could do for suicide but have
dozens of them going on and out of them
someone's gonna spark an idea that's
absolutely amazing and then we've got
like if enough people can see and hear
those conversations and are willing to
be part of the 10,000 you vote on which
one's the best one and you pick it and
then you put the money towards and and
we figure out how to create that right
either someone takes it on as a project
or we take it on collectively as a
project
finding something that's a powerful
adjacent so this is kind of trying to
eventually attract 10,000 people but
it's like wait look we have we have them
but we're figuring that right now it's
it's adjacent possible okay so the
people once have got an idea to go with
because I tried it we're just basically
a seed of an idea and I managed to make
a manager speech about 7,000 people
worldwide just about 15 years ago and I
did it one at a time but as I said there
was just me on my own
I mean iam idea was just to be
half-baked and nobody really got it so
if I've got a plan and an idea I'm
really good to collect in people and
that is it was part of what the solution
raising is - is that like people having
some people are better at attracting
some people have have amazing ideas and
if we can like put those together then
we have the best traceable
she's not gonna figure out how to know
it's like so excited I can't she asked
me how to spell hatching it
hey everybody it's like a new idea dozen
people like how much of your time how
much of their time do you have that's
part of it is they could they would
decide right so maybe a fraction of them
are putting in a lot of time and other
people aren't or maybe they're all
committing to ten hours a month that's
part of what the 10,000 people might
decide together what would you think
would be what is your what's percolating
for that question I don't know about
this issue in particular but in general
with that amount of people you just pose
a more general approach like they come
up with ideas and the best idea somehow
it wins there's some method and then
they all get behind it and they put the
money towards it so just getting a
system like that figured out we'd be
very helpful for this or any other
solution raising it could be a general
solution to any of these sessions you
get five thousand people and hundred
thousand dollars and you this procedure
and then yeah and there could be
multiple multiple procedures that are
like hey which one to you which one
works for this one which one do you
think would work for this one and that
is the vision is that we figured that
kind of out together
and then tweak it figure it out as we go
figure it out like it's it's any of the
possibilities we've come up with you're
in solution raising or amazing but it's
four of us coming up with it right it's
not ten thousand then we define 9996
people to come and give us ten dollars
to make our vision right but if they're
part of it if they're part of creating
it they have their own conversations and
they're watching conversations and
voting and they're what would get you to
put ten dollars in right is this idea
big enough is it a big enough adjacent
possible you would tell friends and put
ten dollars in and then we can get to
those people then we have 10,000 we can
literally just create thing after thing
after thing and if we don't you know we
don't 10,000 for this project we just go
and get more and you don't need to solve
it for the world you just have to solve
it for that
for a collective decision-making and
it's I don't think that voting is the
end all and be all because there's some
real problems with voting like when you
when you vote you're not trying to make
it's not like I'm trying to make the
best possible proposal I'm just trying
to make it better than other people's
proposals and then that creates this
opposition between different proposals
each one trying to be better than the
other as opposed to everybody working
together to figure out how to make these
proposals the best that they can be so I
do first
where if I offer a proposal first thing
we do is everybody tries to help improve
my proposal and make it as best good as
it can be and then other proposal
everybody tries to improve that one etc
and then we have lots of proposals that
are like fully perfected and then maybe
at that point voting would be helpful
but I'm still skeptical because it's
like you think it might turn into a bit
of a popularity contest then yeah
because that's why you know when you you
go online and you see people vote you
know particles this oh if you're my
friend you'll you know vote for me leave
and don't the uncle nuclear was about
before yeah it needs some way to select
the best possibility not just the
possibility that's best at getting votes
at the same time literally any
possibility starts the ball rolling
because then it's not just this is now
the solution till the end of time it's
like great now how do we improve it
right or if this doesn't work for you
how do you start 10 to 10 thousand
person project yeah it doesn't feed off
of it so yes I think all of those things
are problems but it's like creating
something this isn't a democracy like
now you have to use this up right this
is a democracy like hey what kind of
features and benefits would you most
want in it what would you need to be in
it for you to use it what would you
least want to be in it and this would be
different of course if it was an
in-person project like we were talking
about previously people their
involvement in their money basically is
it like an idea then they'll get behind
it but putting ten dollars in and doing
stuff starts that idea helping to
improve it they don't like the idea that
will work on some other idea and start
helping evolve that idea
develop that idea what do you think so
people could be like you know there's a
lot of people in this wait was it time
time polkas rich and cash poor and time
rich right
people have different resources that
they can be yeah and that's also like
for me I I my little brain wants
everyone 10,000 people everyone puts in
$10 because it's fair and we feel it
like we're at equal level
but that doesn't mean that's what 10,000
people might say you know what hundred
dollars is nothing to me
million dollars even right nothing I
want to solve this and somebody else is
like right I got nothing I don't have
money but this is a I'm willing to put
in time and everybody in between and to
empower people to do what is what they
want to do what's the organized such a
large number of people yep
I don't have the mechanisms for this at
the moment no and that's figuring out
the mechanism like part of me wants to
invite like Jordan Hall and Brett
Weinstein and and David daniel
trachtenberg to do a solution raising on
their own without me on whatever topic
because they would bring in literally
ten thousand people no problem between
all of their their things and but and
then it would be like a somewhat
celebrity project right but I don't
think the project would be as good as if
10,000 people put in their say um but it
would could possibly get the people and
that would be then we play in the um the
project right like we prototype what
could be done with as many people it
would be the four people that are
experts talk about any people just vote
on what features and benefits they want
because you can't have 10,000 people
part of a conversation with current
technology and uploading and figuring
things out at work so that it feels good
for the individual they feel like they
contributed a part of it but
you could ask them to be patrons asunder
you what sorry he's asked to be patron
so they know that that's Daniel schmuck
what about I can't pronounce the second
thing thank you what's this
doctor write what I want deeply is for
people who have a lot of followers to
hold solution raisins but more encourage
their people who are watching to hold
solution raisins
this isn't about broadcast this is the
solution it's about get together with
four people and then having a common
place where you can actually put your
idea and then we can vote on it and then
the top three we can help it's not you
know what I mean if Josh comes Joshua
comes up with an amazing project it
isn't then Joshua wasn't he owns in
we're all giving him money it's how do
we now improve it right how do we
improve your idea so then it's now our
idea and maybe we're doing it three with
three different projects at once so then
eventually we get to a point where like
okay now which one are we gonna fund or
people are really set on the one that
they improved and so maybe there's three
thousand three thousand and three
thousand great go out and get another
like how do you grow to ten thousand
before you start a project and then
create all three of them at once and how
can we not feed off of each other's
projects right how can we have a comic
datapool or common people or something
that isn't gonna dissipate it there's
tons of possibility it's just figuring
out anything and it making it better but
if you already have a really cool
project like how do you get how do you
get other people to work on it with you
and funding for it etc really good
question but that we're trying to tackle
it together TAC like yep
we all did interesting unique projects
but no one wants to give up their
project to work on someone else's and we
all would love people to work on them
but the people who know to look for
projects with people with projects not
people who are like hey I have passion
in time put me where you want so it in
terms of so they finding out who's doing
what and Tim's about you know cuz
obviously people are going to be at
different levels of stages of the
projects and that so if I wants to find
look for projects where would it go to
find them we
there was a go to find the writer
problem and we were to go to find out
what people are needed in terms of
skills and time is that anything like
that just now don't think so
I'm not just part of yes that would be
great if that existed there was like a
common place will put their projects and
say here's what I am here's what I need
whether it's game a you know putting in
money and doing that or game you know
come be part of ever gonna create
something different like having it
across the second just like a place like
a Kickstarter but for people like how do
you how do you attract people so you
have to really have a big network to
start off with and you have to spam them
and spam them and found them infect them
and back them you know re because I've
know people who've done them aren't they
ever made the actual funds that they
need so they lost all our money
you know like IndieGoGo so I think I bet
I won because you know at least if
enough makes money you still get four
people are pledged for it's just the
relentless nature that you've actually
got to keep on people's cases every day
you know I mean and that's just sort of
your right to me at all you know I mean
it is I just don't think you should
because like hustling people and
probably where to went wrong last time
it's because it didn't want to ask for
people you know I thought well if people
want to do this they'll come to it of
their own volition
you know we without sorta like Aaron
poked and prodded on a daily basis you
know I mean because then I think that
just tends probably quite a lot of
people off bite so to do that without
both of the people all the time the
closest thing that already exists that I
can think of to a place where there's
lots of projects and people tell each
other about their projects and find
collaborators etc is a co-working space
a co-working space yeah there's a be
part of a committee of that work years
ago I remember joining enough they were
all about sod like getting together and
finding out what what needs for
different projects around the world and
whiteboards actually went to Chicago and
and to meet some of them
as an open-space em me in there and it
was great and as I said I've not come
across and and like that's it's really
because it would actually people who
actually really did the way I can look
but you know because I remember one guy
came on on him he was homeless and you
said he was homeless so now I'm he's
been sleeping in his mom's car well his
parents have died he lost the house and
we sleeping in a car so because I'll
father another network and I noticed
this guy who said on intercom - you're
not - II am do you know anyone who could
give this guy a job because all the
other people in the network could this I
had an IT background but they would all
say no maybe he'd get a job as a cleaner
that's a fuck sakes so I stayed up all
night and I got in touch with this guy
and it's like you did you know anybody
and I didn't come to you maybe
so like see the space and maybe get him
a job than that so he said Hotel town to
comfort a cup of coffee with me so it
did and then I went back in the
substitute era we said no shit what
happened and we're back to the guy and
he said to him oh I am going off my
chore money to just go in four cups of
coffee as a book just go so anyway so in
the end of getting the job and I've got
a message on months but we took about 10
years to save it really happy they
managed to sort of exhorted life out
enough and the guy who was actually
introduced into was Ivan mr. he had to
be a knight in Business Network and
international and I've just chatted so
much so I can you give this anyone in
your networks of people can help him out
and so him and you know Factory said oh
you've done a really good thing but the
people on the network he couldn't see
past I'll just get McLean and job was
get him working in McDonald tonight so
he ended up being the IT guy for this
guy I dismiss now or a tick I didn't
know he's a philanthropist at the time
or that what he said he was I just knew
he had a big network of people who could
actually help people out enough and I
didn't know the guy he was due domeless
and that so I took a big risk way but it
worked out but ya know I ever about and
a couple of weeks ago saying he's
retired now when he was working and the
other places sorry Kerry Kerry my kids
about to interrupt again I just wanna
bring it back to we got definitely off
topic but in a moment a but now we only
have a few minutes left so I would like
to take around we each can share if we
want what the most powerful solution
that was either generated during this
conversation or just comes up to you in
the moment you think the most powerful
thing that we could do with 10,000
people and $100,000 in this space of
suicide just about the clowns I think
develop the plan for it to start off
with and then and that that would be
dumb be a start and develop them to make
the ball concrete to actually go out
there and say right this is what we
doing they're having a place just
somewhere where I could know I could go
to where I could just get help and
whatever was on the other end of that
screen of that space was like there was
a big enough network then we knew we
could support the people coming in where
when you needed someone to sit with you
when you're in crisis there it was there
something that is is simple or and I
just made that way more complicated even
something like that came up while you
were talking the last part carries is
barbecuer who has a powerful TED talk
has this concept of a wish obstacle
where yes it's not tackling suicide but
if you have an obstacle like I don't
have a job and I'm living in my car and
your wish is that you don't want to call
it you want a job but there's someone in
that network to help you and if you know
there's somewhere you can go for help
even if it's not mental health crisis
help it's still like you know you're not
on your own and to be able to yeah yeah
yeah and it could be I'm suicidal I need
someone to sit with me right could be
wish obstacle won't be having it in the
in the bigger network mm-hmm anything
speak to you Joshua that would be
powerful I don't know
all right well thanks for joining it I'm
just going we're gonna stay on because
we're gonna go we're gonna say goodbye
did the recording light